Before we get our hands dirty with
learning how to build a computer,
let's talk theory first.
In an earlier lesson,
we talked about binary, and
how computers perform calculations.
Remember that our computer can only
communicate in binary, using ones and
zeroes.
Our computers speak in machine language,
but we of course speak in human languages,
like English, Spanish, Mandarin, Hindi.
You get the idea.
If we want to communicate
with our machines,
we have to have some
translation dictionary.
Just if I wanted to say
something in Spanish,
I'd look it up in
an English-Spanish dictionary.
Well our computers have
a built-in translation book.
In this lesson, we'll dive deeper into how
our computer translates the information we
give it into instructions
that it understands.
Right now, you're probably using a web
browser, music player, text setter or
something else in your computer.
We interact with these
applications on a daily basis.
They are referred to as Programs.
Programs are basic instructions
that tell the computer what to do.
We technically store programs on
durable media like hard drives.
You can think of programs
like cooking recipes.
We get these recipes all
stored together in a cook book
just like apps stored in a hard drive.
Now we want to make a ton of food.
So we hire a chef to follow our
recipes and whip up something good.
The faster our chef works,
the more food she'll prepare.
The chef is our CPU, she processes the
recipes we send her and makes the food.
Our chef works super fast, so fast that
she can cook faster than she can read.
So, we take copy of the recipes and
put them into RAM.
Remember that RAM is our
computer's short-term memory.
It stores information in
a location our CPU can access
faster than it could with our hard drive.
Now we can give our chef one or
two recipes at a time,
instead of reciting
the entire cookbook to her.
Okay, now let's say I want to make
a peanut butter and jelly sandwich.
I see a pretty good recipe, and
send it to our chef to make.
Remember that our chef needs
these instructions quickly, so
I don't send her the entire recipe,
I send her one line at a time.
1, Get two slices of bread.
2, Put peanut butter on one slide.
3, Put jelly on another slice.
4, Combine the two slices of bread.
Now, let me throw one more thing at you.
Our chef can only communicate
with us in ones and zeroes.
So instead of sending something readable,
like the recipe for a peanut butter and
jelly sandwich,
we have to send her something like this.
In reality,
this process is a little more complicated.
Our CPU is constantly taking
instructions and executing them.
These instructions
are written in binary but
how do they travel around the computer?
In our computer, we have something
called the External Data Bus or EDB.
It's nothing like a bus at all.
It's a row of wires that interconnect
the parts of our computer,
kind of the veins in our body.
When you send a voltage
to one of the wires,
we say the state of the wire is on,
or represented by a 1.
If there's no voltage, then we say that
the state is off, represented by a 0.
This is how we send around our ones and
zeroes.
Sound familiar?
The last lesson we talked about how
transistors help us to send voltages.
Now we know how our bits
physically travel around computer.
The EDB comes in different sizes,
8 bit, 16 bit, 32, even 64.
Can you imagine if you had 64 wires going?
You can move around a lot more data.
Right now, were just going to stick with
using an EDB with 8 bits in our examples.
Sending 1 byte at a time.
Okay so now, our CPU is receiving
a byte and it needs to get to work.
Inside the CPU there
are components known as Registers.
They let us store the data
that our CPU works with.
If for example,
our CPU wanted to add two numbers, one
number would be stored in a register a.
Another number would be
stored in register b.
The result of those two numbers
would be stored in register c.
Imagine the register is one
of our chef's work tables.
Since she has a place to work,
she can start to cook.
To do so she uses a translation book
to translate her binary into tasks
that she can perform.
Let's jump back for a second.
Remember that our programs are copied
into RAM for the CPU to read.
RAM is memory that is randomly accessed,
allowing our CPU to read from any part
of RAM as quickly as any other part.
We don't actually send data
from RAM over the EDB.
There would be way to much stuff.
RAM can hold millions,
even billions, of rows of data.
Despite our sandwich example,
most of our recipes aren't simple at all.
There can be thousands of lines long.
We want to process them and we don't
actually go in any particular order.
Since we can only send one line of
data through the EDB at the time,
we need the help of another component,
the Memory Controller Chip or MCC.
The MCC is a bridge between the CPU and
the RAM.
You can think of it, a nerve in your
brain connecting to your memories.
The CP talks to the MCC, and says,
hey, I need the instructions for
step number three of this recipe.
The MCC finds the instructions for step
number three in RAM, grabs the data, and
sends it through the EDB.
There's another bus.
There's nothing like a bus involved in
the process called the Address bus.
It connects the CPU to the MCC,
and sends over the location of the data,
but not the data itself.
Then the MCC takes the address and
looks for the data.
And then data is then sent over the EDB.
Believe it or not, RAM isn't the fastest
way we can get more data to our CPU for
processing.
The CPU also uses
something known as Cache.
Cache is smaller than RAM, but it let's
us store data that we use often, and
let's us quickly reference it.
Think of RAM like
a refrigerator full of food.
It's easy to get into, but
it takes time to get something out.
On the flip side of that, Cache is
like the stuff we have in our pockets.
It's used to store recently or
frequently accessed data.
There are three different cache
levels in a CPU, L1, L2, and L3.
L1 is the smallest and fastest cache.
If you're interested in
learning more about this,
you can check out the supplemental reading
I've included right after this video.
So now we understand how our
RAM interacts with our CPU.
But how does our CPU know when the set of
instruction ends, and a new one begins.
Our CPU has an internal clock that
keeps its operational in sync.
It connects to a special
wire called Clock wire.
When you send or receive data, it sends a
voltage to that clock wire to let the CPU
know it can start doing calculations.
Think of our clock wires
as the ticking of a clock.
For every tick,
the CPU does one cycle of operations.
When you send a voltage to the clock wire,
it's referred to as a clock cycle.
If you have lots of data you
need to process in a command.
You need to run lots of clock cycles.
Have you ever seen a CPU in the store and
has something labeled 3.4ghz,
this number refers to
the Clock speed of the CPU.
Which is a maximum number of clock cycles
that it can handle in a set in a certain
time period.
3.40 gigahertz is 3.4
billion cycles per second.
That's super fast.
But just because it can run at this speed,
doesn't mean it does.
It just means that it
can't exceed this number.
Still, that number doesn't
stop some people from trying.
There's a way you can exceed
the number of clock cycles
on your CPU on almost any device.
It's referred to as Overclocking and
it increases the rate of your CPU clock
cycles in order to perform more tasks.
This is commonly used to increase
the performance in low-end CPUs.
Let's say you're a gamer and
you want to have better graphics and
less lag while playing.
You might want to overclock your
CPU when you play the game, but
there are cons to doing this,
like potentially overheating your CPU.
You can read more about overclocking
in the next supplementary reading.