You've gained a lot of great
foundational troubleshooting skills.
But there is some common pitfalls
that you should try to avoid
in order to be at the top of
your troubleshooting game.
As an IT support specialist,
you'll sometime encounter the same
issue over and over again.
Before the next issue comes in,
you may find yourself using your
muscle memory to fix the issue.
Pitfall #1, going into autopilot.
Make sure you don't
default to autopilot mode,
moving through issues out of habit and
without careful thought.
More often than not there
are small variables that
change the problem you're seeing entirely.
Ask questions and gather data so
you can fully understanding an issue.
This takes less time than having to
redo some sloppy work you did in
autopilot mode.
Pitfall #2, not finding the root cause.
It's very easy to get distracted
by small problems that pop up.
But it's super important to remember
there's probably a very big problem
causing all these small problems.
Spend a little extra time
investigating the issue
instead of trying to fix
all the small holes.
If you're trying do a quick fix,
it's tempting to wipe a system and
start from scratch.
This approach is kind of like using
a hammer when a surgical scalpel might be
a more appropriate tool.
Let's say a user isn't able to
access a particular website.
Re-imaging the system isn't a great solve.
It doesn't get to the root cause, and it
doesn't help further your own knowledge.
Investigating the problem of it,
testing out possible issues and solutions
incrementally, and identifying the root
cause can end up saving a lot of time and
effort in the end, and it feels really
empowering as an IT support specialist.
And with that, you'll be able
to go out in the real world and
use your new skills to methodically
troubleshoot an issue.