Imagine this scenario.
You're playing your favorite video game,
and you finally get to the big boss.
You spent countless
hours finding this boss,
neglecting all other responsibilities
like your job, school, even hygiene.
That's pretty gross, but I get it.
So you're right about to kill
the big boss when suddenly
your game console shuts off completely.
You probably freak out for a second.
But then you remember, it's okay, you
saved the game before the boss came along.
So now you can turn it back on,
and you'll be at the same spot.
But then your console shuts off again,
this happens over and over.
You, like most people, are devastated.
You fly into a fit of rage, but then,
just before you toss your console out,
you make one last ditch effort and
yell, tell me what's wrong with you.
Suddenly you hear a faint voice
telling you what you want to hear.
Wouldn't that be amazing?
Sure, that scenario was a bit exaggerated.
But my point is that our computers
actually can talk to us and
tell us what's wrong.
Maybe they won't whisper answers to us,
but they speak to us in the form of logs.
Logs are files that record
system events on our computer
just like a system's diary.
Our computer will record events like when
it was turned on, when a driver was loaded
and even when something isn't working
in the form of error messages.
In all operating systems, logs are kept so
we can refer back to them when we need
to find out something that happened.
But logs can be hard to navigate
because our computer will
essentially record everything.
Here's what a log looks like.
As you can see, it can be tough
to make your way through a log.
But, with a little bit of elbow grease,
we can figure out what happened on our
computer and piece together a solution.
We'll see an example of how a log
is useful in figuring out an issue
in a later lesson.
We'll dive into the technical
details of logs in a later course.
For now, just be aware that we can
investigate details about our computer
that aren't obvious to us.
Unfortunately, our computers,
cars and machines
don't have a little voice that tells
us what's wrong when there's a problem.
But by the end of this program, you'll
be able to navigate and read logs, so
you won't even need it.