You're doing awesome. By now you've learned what software is,
how it integrates with our computer, and how we manage it.
It was easy to install,
update, and remove software on one machine.
But what if you had to do that for multiple machines?
That would take up a lot of time.
If only there was a way we could have it done automatically for us.
Spoiler alert, there is.
We use software to help us with this.
There are lots of tools out there that help make managing computers easier.
We use automation for this.
Automation makes processes work automatically.
You can even use the tools of automation like programs
and scripts to help you with troubleshooting issues.
So instead of reading hundreds of lines of log files
manually to discover when a particular error occurred on a computer,
you could write a script to read the log for you and print out only the relevant line,
we'll learn a lot more about automation later.
Just know that software has many uses
including making processes more efficient and easier.
You made it all the way through software, nice work.
We'll meet again in course five, IT Automation,
it's not that scary, really it's not.
I'm excited to show you the power of
automation and teach you some of the actual coding in Ruby.
Next, you'll meet Marty Clark,
she's your instructor for troubleshooting and will talk to you
about how good customer service is critical to IT support.
In the meantime, work hard,
soak up a ton of knowledge,
and have some fun along the way.
I'll see you back here later on.