Now that we've talked a little
bit about documenting processes,
let's talk about how you'll write
documentation in ticketing or bug system.
You don't have to leave a full
example of process documentation for
every ticket you handle.
If you encounter the same issue,
just write the documentation once,
then refer back to it.
One of the more important aspects of
writing documentation in a ticket or
bug is that you leave an audit trail
to see what worked and what didn't.
Let's take a look at some examples
of awesome documentation and
not-so-awesome documentation
in ticketing and bug systems.
This isn't helpful at all,
since we don't know what the issue was, or
what the IT support
specialist did to fix it.
If someone stumbled upon this
ticket with the same issue,
it would be pretty useless.
This is an example of
a great ticket documentation.
A tech described what the issue is,
what caused the issue,
and the specific steps
they took to resolve it.