Always remember, that people use technology to make their lives better,
easier and more productive.
They can get discouraged,
angry or frustrated when the technology which they may not fully understand.
Doesn't respond like they expect as an I.T.
support specialist, you have the opportunity to leverage your technical knowledge,
to fix the problem and understand impact that issue might have on the user.
This means, you're uniquely positioned to directly improve people's lives.
You'll solve technical problems and make them feel better in the process.
The skills you learned in this module,
should benefit you throughout your entire career in the I.T.
world. As you know by now,
to be great at customer service sometimes you need to take
a moment to pause, reflect and listen.
How about we give that a shot now.
Stop what you're doing for a minute and think about what you've achieved.
You're so close to finishing this course,
you should be really proud of the time and effort
you've put in to prepare for a career in I.T.
support. Now there's just one more thing to check off.
We're going to test what you've learned in our lesson on documentation.
Be sure to take your time and think through
all the different steps in the problem. You've got this.