You may have heard of the phrase Internet of Things or IoT.
This concept is pretty new but already has a major impact on the future of computing.
The concept is fairly simple.
Basically, more and more devices are
being connected to the internet in a smarter fashion.
Did you know that there are now smart thermostats?
Instead of manually programming them when you'll be out of the house,
they'll just know when you leave and turn off the air conditioning for you.
And it's not just your thermostat,
many companies out there are making smarter household devices.
There are fridges that can keep track of what foods you have in their,
toasters that can be controlled by your smartphone,
lights that can change depending on your mood and
cars that drive you instead of you driving them.
The world is moving towards connecting
manual devices to the internet and making them smarter.
These decisions have many societal implications though,
especially when it comes to cybersecurity or personal privacy.
But there's also a huge potential for IoT to
completely transforme the world in ways we have yet to see.
In the future, people may be shocked to learn that we had to do manual things like,
make your own coffee or drive to the grocery store.
While you may not experience working with an Internet of Things device,
you should be aware that it will become a large part of the future of computing.
You can learn more about IoT in the next supplementary reading.